[Music]
hello everyone and welcome to this lunch
event session on flexible update
management uh my name is y and I'm
co-presenting with Ricardo
today um flexible update management
we've had for a few months now it's been
in public preview throughout um 2024
Wave 2 and now with 2025 Wave 1 we're
very excited for it to reach General
availability um in short flexible update
management lets administrators schedule
environment updates with more
flexibility um and this can help meet
the requirements of update ADV verse
customers so you might think of a
customer that runs a 24-hour shop and
doesn't want to go through an update
every month or a customer that has
extensive testing requirements and
simply needs more time for each update
um that they install and secondly this
will also help reduce the workload of
partners that are scheduling their
environment updates for their customers
over a longer periods so that they can
spread that workload over the entire
year rather than have Peaks uh whenever
major updates come out
um major minor updates are coming in a
major update cycle now the major update
cycle starts with a preview period
during this period um administrators can
create a Sandbox environment on the new
version to test the new functionality
before the update becomes available on
their production environment once this
preview period is over um we go into the
update period now with flexible update
management this update period is always
five calendar months with a fixed end
date meaning that the major update comes
out every April we'll have an update
period that ends at the end of August
and every major update that comes out in
October we have an update period that
ends at the end of
February after this update period we now
move on into a grace period this is a
one month period um during which we will
attempt the update uh every week so it's
no longer possible to pick any date the
update will run if it fails we will
reschedule it to take place seven days
after the original date if it succeeds
you're out of the grace period and into
the update period for the next major
version um during this period this
update cannot be postponed any further
so we'll schedule it it will run at the
date that we schedule and if it succeeds
you're on to the next update
period if your environment fails to
update during the grace period so um
we've tried to update it a couple times
during the grace period it has not
succeeded we then move on into the
enforced update period uh during which
we'll Force the update to succeeds by
uninstalling any apps that are not
compatible with the next
version um what's important about this
this uninstalled apps is that we will
uninstall the app but we will not delete
the data so if you later on install
compatible version of this app the data
will be available
again um minor updates uh are the same
in two ways so first of all we'll
continue to ship a minor update in every
month um that we're not shipping a major
update so every month except April and
October um the default scheduling of
these minor updates is also unchanged so
if you choose not to use any of the
flexible update management features
your environment will continue to
receive an update every month and will
be installed at the date that Microsoft
schedules of course you can now choose
not to do these minor updates so it's
possible to skip minor updates and you
can opt out of scheduling them
automatically by scheduling an update to
a later version before a minor update
comes out and that kind of goes into the
fourth bullet here where you can select
a Target version for an update so if
you're on let's say version 25.3 today
you can choose to update uh to version
26.3 next and Skip any versions that are
in between those
two and finally what's new is that you
can now create uh environments on any
supported version so during the update
periods for version 26 uh which will run
between April and August 2025 you'll be
able to create new environments on
version 25 or on version
26 so looking at the calendar for 2025
this is what our update cycle looks like
um it's April now so we've just
completed the update cycle for
environments to update from version 24
to version
25 um this version was released first in
October so the update period ran until
the end of February we've had a one
month grace period in March and now it's
April we're forcing any environments
that have not updated yet to complete
this
update um at the same time of this grace
period during March we run the preview
for version 26 and now that is April the
the regular update period has run and
will continue to run until the end of
August
after which again we'll um have a grace
period in September and a force update
period starting in
October and finally version 27 later
this year when it comes out in in
September will follow the same pattern
where the preview period overlaps with
the grace period and the force update
period starts when the regular updates
to version 27
start um what's new with flexible update
management now that it's generally
available is that it's available
globally so the past few months this is
only applied to Microsoft localized
environments starting with 2025 release
wave 1 um this is now available globally
so also on environment localizations
that are not localized by Microsoft um
you also start to see the admin sensor
changes come in so you'll be able to
choose a specific Target version for
your next environment update you'll be
able to opt out of an update until
specified Target version rard will show
you how that works and you'll be able to
now create environments on any
version um finally there's also API
changes so the the API that we've had
for years to manage environment updates
will continue to work uh but it will not
support any of the new flexibility that
we're introducing here so if you're
using the API to schedule updates across
all of your environments I'd recommend
that you look at the new API end points
to use this new flexibility uh in your
automations as well and now to see what
it looks like in the admin Center
Ricardo yeah thank you use so I will be
glad to show you how you as a tenant
administrator can leverage the new
flexible update management capabilities
in the admin Center so let's just jump
straight into a demo so I am a tenant
administrator indeed and I am already in
the environment Details page I have my
production environment open right here
so what stands out now is that we have
repurposed a little bit this panel down
here which is now called update settings
and it provides a little bit um slightly
different information compared to what
we used to show here so first of all you
can notice we are running currently home
version 25.0 so major minor version is
25 and currently at this point in time
we have the latest available version
that we can choose for an update is 25.5
So currently it means 25.5 is the latest
available version on which we can create
environments and update these
environment to so then we have this uh
section here called next update which
will tell tell us at this point in time
what is the next Target version that
this environment will be updated to and
on which
date and lastly but not least uh what is
the latest date after which um the grace
period will
start um that we can update our
environment to the next major version so
in this case it will be 26.0 so in other
words we are allowed to stay on version
25.0 until these cut of date after that
date The Grace update period will start
and then we will begin with these weekly
update
attempts so what happens now when we
want to reschedule our update or pick a
different Target version so if we click
on modify here then the usual schedule
environment update fly out opens up and
we already noticed that something is
different here because now we have the
choice of the target version we can pick
any available Target version uh that is
currently already that has currently
already been released and those are
marked as
available and additionally we are also
offered the possibility to pick any
unreleased version up to version 26.4 so
we have already mentioned 26.0 at this
point in time has not been released yet
then we are free to choose any version
up to 26.4 so let's imagine I want to
actually skip one of the next immediate
minor updates I want to Target get my
environment already to version
25.4 so um we can already see that as
usual we can select an update date
anytime in the future so let's pick just
a date for this and schedule the
update then of course this is
immediately reflected in this cell right
here we can now see it's pointing 25.4
on this date but what if instead I want
to pick a version that has not been
released yet so it is planned for some
later time in the future so let's say
imagine that I pick 26.2 planned for
June 2025 so at this point we cannot
pick a Target update date for this
version because the message here will
indeed tell us that the update will
automatically be scheduled after within
14 days um since the since this specific
version is released so it will be
Microsoft internally who schedules the
version who schedules the update to 26.2
for this environment and at that point
tenant administrators will still be able
to reschedule the update to any other uh
date in the future so if I pick this
target version this is again reflected
here slightly differently we can see we
are targeting
26.2 scheduled upon release so if I
navigate back to the environments list
page we can see this choice is also
refle Ed in the schedule update date
column and in next update we can see we
are targeting 26.2 but the schedule
update date is not scheduled because of
course we haven't we we were not able to
pick a specific date for this target
version at this point in time but when
the update becomes available and it is
scheduled then of course a new date will
show up
here okay so now that we're done with
the demo let's uh jump into some of the
best practi practices that come uh
taking into considerations the new
capabilities offered by flexible update
management so of course we've seen that
historically speaking majority of the
environments could keep up with the
latest versions though they are usually
sticking to the latest available
versions and they can be updated with no
issues however we do know that there are
some environments that may actually
start lagging behind with the latest
version so this is when you can benefit
from the flexibility uh offered by this
new this new feature um but that of
course comes with extra considerations
about keeping your environments in an
updatable State uh it's important that
you stay current with the extension so
that you can always make sure that they
are compatible with the target versions
that you eventually want to Target for
your environments and therefore it's
also important to stay updated on the
product changes uh be aware of the
what's new um documentation that we
always publish with every new version
that is available in business
Central thank you thank you for watching